接下来我们看然后计算大整数的模
The next thing we're going to look at is
how to compute modular large integers. So
第一个问题是，我们如何在计算机里表示大整数？
the first question is how do we represent
large integers in a computer? So that's
这点还是很直接的。假设我们有一台64位机
actually fairly straightforward. So
imagine we're on a 64 bit machine, what we
我们把想表示的大数进行分割，32位一组
would do is we would break the number we
want to represent, into 32 bit buckets. And
然后，我们会有n/32个组
then, we will basically have these n/32 bit buckets, and together they will
它们可以表示这个数，我们想把它存储在计算机上
represent the number that we want to store
on the computer. Now, I should mention
现在，我应该说，我只是拿64位寄存器作个例子
that I'm only giving 64 bit registers as
an example. In fact, many modern
事实上很多现代处理器都有128位寄存器或更多，
你可以在上面计算乘法
processors have 128 bit registers or more,
and you can even do multiplications on
一般情况下，你会使用长于32位的分组
them. So normally you would actually use
much larger blocks than just 32 bits. The
你想限制到32位是因为这样一来
reason, by the way, you want to limit
yourself to 32 bits is so that you can
你可以把两个分组乘在一起，而结果小于64位
multiply two blocks together, and the
result will still be less than 64 bits,
小于机器字长。现在我们来看特定的
less than the word size on the machine. So
now let's look at particular arithmetic
算术操作，看看它们会花多少时间。那么加法和减法
operations and see how long each one
takes. So addition and subtraction
你要注意加法有进位，减法有借位
basically what you would do is that
addition would carry or subtraction would
这些都是线性时间操作。换句话说
borrow and those are basically linear time
operations. In other words, if you want to
如果你想加或减两个n位整数，运行时间
add or subtract two n bit integers the
running time is basically
与n成线性。天然的乘法会花平方时间。事实上
linear in n. Multiplication
naively will take quadratic time. In fact,
这是高中的算法，大家在高中学到的
this is what's called the high school
algorithm. This is what you kind of
如果大家想想，就会看出
learned in school, where if you think
about this for a minute you'll see that,
这个算法的时间与乘数的长度的平方成正比
that algorithm basically is quadratic in
the length of the numbers that are being
令人惊奇的是，在1960年代Karatsuba提出一个算法
multiplied. So a big surprise in the 1960s
was an algorithm due to Karatsuba that
(Karatsuba是苏联数学家)
可以取得比平方时间快得多的性能
actually achieves much better than
quadratic time in fact, it achieved a
事实上，它的运行时间是n^1.585。
这里我不需要告诉大家
running time of n to the 1.585. And
there's actually no point in me showing
这个算法是如何工作的。我只是提一下大致思想
you how the algorithm actually worked,
I'll just mention the main idea what
Karatsuba当时发现的。事实上，当你想乘两个数时
Karatsuba realized, is that in fact when
you want to multiply two numbers, you can
你可以取第一个乘数x，把它写成2^b乘以x2
write them as, you can take the first
number x, write it as 2 to the b times
加上x1，这里x2和x1大约是x的平方根大小
x2 plus x1. Where x2 and x1 are roughly
the size of the square root of x. Okay, so
那么我们可以把x分解成左边的x和右边的x
we can kind of break the number x into the
left part of x and the right part of x.
你用2的b次方来表示x
And basically, you're writing x as if it
was written base 2 to the b. So it's got
得到2的b次方进制的两个数位。你对y做同样的事
two digits base 2 to the b. And you do
the same thing with, y. You write y base
你以2的b次方来表示y。你也会把y写成左边
2 to the b. Again, you would write it
as, the sum of the left half plus the
加上右边的形式，然后，如果你试着计算这个乘法
right half, And then, normally, if you try
to do this multiplication, when you open
当你展开这些括号时，你会发现，这需要4个乘法
up the parentheses. You see that, this
would require 4 multiplications, right?
它需要计算x2乘y2，x2乘y1，x1乘y2，x1乘y1
It would require x2 times y2, x2 times y1,
x1 times y2, and x1 times y1. What
Karatsuba发现有一种方法可以计算x乘以y
Karatsuba realized is there's a way to do
this multiplication of x by y using only
只需3个x1,x2,y1,y2的乘法。计算x和y的大乘法
three multiplications of x1 x2 y1 y2. So it's just a big multiplication of x times y
只需计算3个小乘法
only it takes three little multiplications. You can now recursively
你现在可以递归地应用同样的流程
来计算x2乘y2，x2乘y1，等等
apply exactly the same procedure to
multiplying x2 by y2, and x2 by y1, and so
你会得到这个递归算法
on and so forth. And you would get this
recursive algorithm. And if you do the
如果你进行递归分析，你会看到运行时间是n^1.585
recursive analysis, you will see that
basically, you get a running time of n to the 1.585.
这里的1.585其实是log_2 3
This number is basically, the 1.585 is basically, log of 3 base 2.
(T(n)=3T(n/2)+O(1)=O(n^(log_2 3)))
令人惊奇的是，实际上Karatsuba还不是最好的乘法算法
Surprisingly, it turns out that Karatsuba
isn't even the best multiplication
实际上你可以用大约n log(n)的时间来计算乘法
algorithm out there. It turns out that, in fact, you can do multiplication in about n log(n) time.
那么你可以用几乎线性的时间来计算乘法。但是
这是一个极为渐近的结果
So you can do multiplication in almost linear time. However, this is an extremely asymptotic results.
这个大O记号忽略了很大的常数
The big O here hides very big constants. And as a
因此这个算法只有当乘数非常巨大的时候
result, this algorithm only becomes
practical when the numbers are absolutely
才会变得实用。那么这个算法实际上用的不多
enormous. And so this algorithm is
actually not used very often. But
但Karatsuba算法很常用。事实上大多数的密码学库
Karatsuba's algorithm is very practical.
And in fact, most crypto-libraries
都用的是Karatsuba算法来实现乘法。但是
implement Karatsuba's algorithm for
multiplication. However, for simplicity
这里我就忽略了Karatsuba算法的细节，为求简单
here, I'm just gonna ignore Karatsuba's
algorithm, and just for simplicity, I'm
我假设乘法运行在平方时间里。但大家应该始终认为
gonna assume that multiplication runs in
quadratic time. But in your mind, you
乘法应该比平方时间稍快些
should always be thinking all multiplication really is a little bit faster than quadratic.
乘法之后，下一个问题是
And then the next question after multiplication is what about
关于带余数的除法，实际上这也是个平方时间算法
division with remainder and it turns out
that's also a quadratic time algorithm.
剩下的主要问题是，一个我们目前已经用了很多次的
So the main operation that remains, and one
that we've used many times so far, and
但我却从未告诉大家如何计算它的东西
I've never, actually never, ever told you
how to actually compute it, is this
就是求幂的问题。那么我们来抽象一点地解决
question of exponentiation. So let's solve
this exponentiation problem a bit more
这个指数问题。那么设想一下，我们有一个有限循环群G
abstractly. So imagine we have a finite
cyclic group G. All this means is that
这意味着这个群是由生成元g的各个幂生成的
this group is generated from the powers of
some generator little g. So for example
比如想想群Z_p^*，g是某个G的生成元
think of this group as simply ZP*, and think of little g as some generator of
我这样做的原因是想让大家适应
big G. The reason I'm sitting in this way,
is I'm, I want you to start getting used
这种抽象，我们在处理一个普通的群，而Z_p^*
to this abstraction where we deal with a
generic group G and ZP really is just
仅仅是一个例子。但事实上还有很多有限循环群的例子
one example of such a group. But, in fact,
there are many other examples of finite
我想再强调一下群G
cyclic groups. And again I want to
emphasis basically that group G, all it
是由其生成元的所有幂组成，共有群的阶数个幂
is, it's simply this powers of this
generator up to the order of the group.
我写成g^q。那么现在我们的目标是，给定这个生成元g
I'll write it as G to the Q. So our goal
now is given this element g, and some
以及某个指数x，我们的目标是计算g^x
exponent x, our goal is to compute the
value of g to the x. Now normally what you
通常情况下你会认为，如果x=3
would say is, you would think well, you
know, if x is equal to 3 then I'm
我要计算g^3。没有太多办法
gonna compute you know, g cubed. Well,
there's really nothing to do. All I do is
我只能计算g*g*g，获得g^3，记为所求
I just do g times g times g and I get g
cubed, which is what I wanted. So that's
那很容易。但事实上，这不是我们感兴趣的情况
actually pretty easy. But in fact, that's
not the case that we're interested in. In
在我们的情况下，指数将非常巨大。所以如果你去试
our case, our exponents are gonna be
enormous. And so if you try, you know,
想象一个500位的指数，如果试图去计算g的500位次方
think of like a 500-bit number and so if
you try to compute g to the power of a
计算类似于g*g*g*...要花不少时间的
500-bit number simply by multiplying g by
g by g by g this is gonna take quite a
事实上这会花掉指数级时间，这不是我们想要的
while. In fact it will take exponential
time which is not something that we want
问题是尽管x非常大，我们能否依然很快地计算g^x？
to do. So the question is whether even
though x is enormous, can we still compute
答案是肯定的，相应的算法叫做
g to the x relatively fast and the answer
is yes and the algorithm that does that
重复平方算法。我来告诉大家重复平方算法如何工作
is called a repeated squaring algorithm.
And so let me show you how repeated
我们看个例子，53。你要计算53个g的乘积
squaring works. So let's take as an
example, 53. Naively you would have to do
g*g*g*g*..一共53个g
53 multiplications of g by g by g by g
until you get to g by the 53 but I want to
但我想告诉大家，可以很快地做这个计算。
我们把53写成二进制
show you how you can do it very quickly.
So what we'll do is we'll write 53 in
那么这是53的二进制表示
binary. So here this is the binary
representation of 53. And all that means
这意味着，大家注意这个1代表32，这个1代表16
is, you notice this one corresponds to 32,
this one corresponds to 16, this one
这个1代表4，这个1代表1，所以53是
corresponds to 4, and this one
corresponds to 1. So really 53 is 32
32+16+4+1。这意味着g的53次方
plus 16 plus 4 plus 1. But what
that means is that g to the power of 53 is
就是g的32+16+4+1次方。我们可以把指数分解开
g to the power of 32+16+4+1. And we can
break that up, using again, the rules of
再次使用指数法则，我们可以把g^53分解成
g^32乘g^16乘g^4
exponentiation. We can break that up as g
to the 32 times g to the 16 times g to the
乘g^1，现在这应该能给大家一个如何计算g^53的想法了
4 times g to the 1, Now that should start
giving you an idea for how to compute g to
我们取g，然后开始计算平方
the 53 very quickly. What we'll do is,
simply, we'll take g and we'll start
由g想得到g^2，再平方一次
squaring it. So what square wants, g wants
to get g squared. We square it again to
得到g^4，接着是g^8, g^16, g^32
get g to the 4, turn g to the 8.
Turn g to the 16, g to the 32. So
所以我们计算了所有的这些g的平方。现在
we've computed all these squares of g. And
now, what we're gonna do is we're simply
我们简单地乘合适的幂，就可以得到g^53
gonna multiply the appropriate powers to
give us the g to the 53. So this is g to
这是g^1*g^4*g^16*g^32
the one times g to the 4 times g to the 16 times g to the 32, is basically
即为所求值g^53。那么这里大家看到了
gonna give us the value that we want,
which is g to the 53. So here you see that
我们必须做的计算，数一下，1，2，3，4
all we had to do was just compute, let's
see, we had to do one, two, three, four,
5次平方，再加4次乘法，所以通过9步乘法
five squaring, plus four more multiplications
so with 9 multiplications we computed g
我们计算出了g^53。这是很有趣的。实际上
to the 53. Okay so that's pretty
interesting. And it turns out this is a
这是很一般的现象，可以让我们很快地计算g的极高次幂
general phenomena that allows us to raise
g to very, very high powers and do it very
我来为大家展示这个算法，我叫它重复平方算法
quickly. So let me show you the algorithm,
as I said this is called the repeated
算法的输入是元素g
squaring algorithm. So the input to the
algorithm is the element g and the
和指数x。输出是g^x
exponent x. And the output is g to the x.
So what we're gonna do is we're gonna
我们把x写成二进制表示。不妨设x有n位
write x in binary notation. So let's say
that x has n bits. And this is the actual
这是x的二进制位表示。然后我们做如下事情
bit representation of x as a binary
number. And then what we'll do is the
我们有两个寄存器。y是一个总是做平方运算的寄存器
following. We'll have these two registers.
y is gonna be a register that's constantly
z是一个累加器
squared. And then z is gonna be an
accumulator that multiplies in the
计算g的幂的乘法。我们只需循环
appropriate powers of g as needed. So all
we do is the following we loop through the
x的位数那么多轮，从最低位开始
bits of x starting from the least
significant bits, And then we do the
然后我们做如下事情：每轮循环中，我们平方y
following: in every iteration we're simply
gonna square y. Okay, so y just keeps on
y每轮都被平方，然后当x中对应位是1时
squaring at every iteration. And then
whenever the corresponding bit of the
我们让累加器z去累乘y的当前值
exponent x happens to be one, we simply
accumulate the current value of y into
最后我们输出z。完事，即为整个算法
this accumulator z and then at the end, we
simply output z. That's it. That's the
这就是重复平方算法
whole algorithm, and that's the repeated
squaring algorithm. So, let's see an
那么我们看一个g^53的例子。大家可以看到这两栏
example with G to the 53. So,
you can see the two columns. y is one
y是一栏，表示每轮y的演进；z是另一栏
column, as it evolves through the
iterations, and z is another column, again
表示每轮z的演进。y没什么意思
as it evolves through the iterations. So,
y is not very interesting. Basically, all
每过一轮，y被平方
that happens to y is that at every
iteration, it simply gets squared. And so
计算平方，得到幂，完事
it just walks through the powers of two
and the exponents and that's it. z is the
z是个更有趣的寄存器，它累乘着合适的
more interesting register where what it
does is it accumulates the appropriate
g的幂，对应于指数是1的那些位。例如
powers of g whenever the corresponding bit
to the exponent is one. So for example the
指数的第一位是1，因此，在第一轮结束后
first bit of the exponent is one,
therefore, the, at the end of the first
z的值就等于g。指数的第二位是0
iteration the value of z is simply equal to
g. The second bit of the exponent is zero
所以第二轮结束后，z的值不变
so the value of z doesn't change after the
second iteration. And at the end of the
指数的第三位是1，在第三轮结束后
third iteration well the third bit of the
exponent is one so we accumulate g to the
我们用z累乘了g^4。指数的下一位是0，z不变
fourth into z. The next bit of the
exponent is zero so z doesn't change. The
指数的下一位是1，所以现在我们累乘y的值
next bit of the exponent is one and so now
we're supposed to accumulate the previous
到累加器z，我问大家z的值是多少？
value of y into the accumulator z so let
me ask you so what's gonna be the value of z?
我们把g^16次方累乘到z
Well, we simply accumulate g to the
16 into z and so we simply compute the sum
16+5=21。最终，最后一位是1
of 16 and 5 we get g to the 21.
Finally, the last bit is also set to one
所以我们累乘进z，32+21=53，我们输出g^53
so we accumulate it into z, we do 32 plus 21 and we get the finally output g to the 53.
好，这就给大家一个重复平方算法的思路
Okay, so this gives you an idea of how
this repeated squaring algorithm works.
这个算法很有趣，可以让我们计算g的极高次幂
It's is quite an interesting algorithm and
it allows us to compute enormous powers of
以非常快的速度。那么循环次数
g very, very, very quickly. So the number
of iterations here, essentially, would be
是log_2 x。好。大家注意循环次数
log base 2 of x. Okay. You notice the
number of iterations simply depends on the
取决于x的位数，即log_2 x
number of digits of x, which is basically
the log base 2 of x. So even if  x is a
即使x有500位，500次乘法、500次循环
500 bit number in 500 multiplication,
well, 500 iterations, really 1,000
约1000次乘法，因为我们必须计算平方和累乘
multiplications because we have to square
and we have to accumulate. So in 1,000
所以1000次乘法以内，我们就可以求出g的500位次方
multiplications we'll be able to raise g
to the power of a 500 bit exponent.
那么现在我们可以小结一下运行时间
Okay so now we can summarize kind of the running times so suppose we
假设我们有一个N位模，我们说过，Z_N上的加减法
have an N bit modulus capital N as we
said addition and subtraction in ZN takes
花线性时间。我说过，Karatsuba让乘法计算更有效
linear time. Multiplication of just, you
know, as I said, Karatsuba's actually makes this
为求简化，我们说乘法需平方时间
more efficient, but for simplicity we'll
just say that it takes quadratic time. And
然后对于指数，如我所说，需要log(x)次循环
then exponentiation, as I said, basically
takes log of x iterations, and at each
每轮我们做两次乘法，所以它是O(log(x))次乘法
iteration we basically do two
multiplications. So it's O(log (x))
我们说过乘法是时间是平方的
times the time to multiply. And let's say
that the time to multiply is quadratic. So
所以运行时间将是N^2 log(x)
the running time would be, really, N
squared log x. And since x is always gonna
根据费马小定理，x总是小于N，没有必要去计算
be less than N, by Fermat's theorem
there's no point in raising g to a power
g的次数大于模的幂。所以x小于N
that's larger than the modulus. So x is
gonna be less than N. Let's suppose that x
我们假设x也是N位整数，那么指数算法是立方时间算法
is also an N-bit integer, then, really
exponentiation is a cubic-time algorithm.
我希望大家记住的是，指数运算其实很慢
Okay so that's what I wanted you to
remember, that exponentiation is actually
现在，在现代计算机上，指数运算要花几个毫秒
a relatively slow. These days, it actually
takes a few microseconds on a modern
但是对于GHz级的处理器来说
computer. But still, microseconds for a,
for a, say a four gigahertz processor is
毫秒级已是巨大的工作了。所以记住
quite a bit of work. And so just keep in
mind that all the exponentiation
我们讨论过的所有求指数的操作，比如，
判断一个数是否是二次剩余的
operations we talked about. For example,
for determining if a number is a quadratic
所有这些指数操作都要花立方时间的
residue or not, All those, all those
exponentiations basically take cubic time.
那么我们的模算法讨论完结
Okay, so that completes our discussion of
arithmetic algorithms, and then in the
下节我们开始讨论质数模、合数模的难题
next segment we'll start talking about
hard problems, modulo, primes and composites.